# 大家好 今天天氣比較好
Hi everyone! The weather today is quite good.
# 我幫我老媽犁一下那個田
I'm gonna help my mom plough the field.
# 因為那個犁那個田 那工作量有點大
Cuz, you know, ploughing the field requires a lot of work.
# 它老是要抖 抖的全身都不舒服的
It shakes and shakes and shakes. It makes you feel really awful.
# 所以幫她搞一下
That's why I'm helping her,
# 她就沒那麼累
to share her burden.
# 用來種一些蔬菜之類的 (註︰這句很奇怪，應該是突然轉換話題)
It's for plant, planting the veggies or whatever.
# 在這上面一點
It's just a bit up there.
# 我先把那個火打著
I start the engine first.
# 搞這個腰有一點累的哦
This work hurts your lower back.
# 這個腰啊 很累的 它要這樣 這樣駝背 駝著
I mean the lower back, is really tired. You need to bend, bend you back, like this.
# 所以這個腰很累
So the lower back is really tired.
# 我去拿一個
I'm gonna fetch a,
# 拿一個那個床單 到河邊水 (註︰那不是床單好吧....)
fetch a, well, a sleeping mat (raft), to the riverside.
# 河邊去游一下游
to the riverside and have a swim.
# 不是游泳 坐一下那個 那個水船
No, not swim. I mean, have a ride one a, you know, a boat(raft),
# 那河裡面
on the river.
# 哇 太累啦
Wa! I'm exhausted.
# 把這個 這個床單丟到河裡面去
Let me throw the, throw the sleeping mat onto the river first.
# 等一下 我就直接跳到上面去就行弓
Then I can, simply hop onto it right away.
# 哎喲
Ayo!
# 那麼深的
It's so deep!
# 踩了一個坑
I stepped into the pit.
# 差一點就摔下去啦
I almost fell.
# 可以喲
It's not bad!
# 不要棍 (唔愛掍)
I don't need the pole!
# 可以喲
It's not bad!
# 就這樣漂著 讓它漂
So it's drifting. Just let it drift.
# 漂到哪裡算哪裡 反正下面過不行
It doesn't matter where it drifts to. The downstream is blocked anyway.
# 怕不怕
Are you scared?
# 氣死我啦 (註︰以往這句我會譯"Damn it"，但這次出自刘星辰....)
You guys are too bad!
# 扔石頭去
I'll throw them a rock!
# 不要扔 刘星辰
Don't throw! Liu Xinchen!
# 不要扔
Don't throw!
# (刘星辰，聽話一點哦)
Liu Xinchen, be a good boy!
# (睡覺呀，你怕不怕？)
Have a nap. Are you scared?
# 刘星辰
Liu Xinchen!
# (不可以 上來玩 上來玩
No! Come up here, up here!
# 怕不怕 去 把你抱上去 快點
Are you scared? C'mon! I'll take you back. C'mon!
# (過來 刘星辰)
Come here! Liu Xinchen!
# (刘星辰過來 快點) (註︰這以下很多對話都沒有字幕，我把聽得懂的都做一點，讓不懂中文的觀眾可以更投入)
Liu Xinchen! Come here! Hurry up!
# (等一下來 等一下來 XX就會給你們啊)
A moment, a moment! It'll be your turn.
# (啊 我來)
Let me take her!
# (上來啊 妹妹)
Come here, girl!
# (上來啊)
Come here!
# (她不抓)
She's not holding.
# (不要去啊)
Stay here!
# (走啦 刘星辰)
We're leaving, Liu Xinchen!
# (你爸爸也起來啦)
You dad is also coming.
# (等一下 把你爸爸帶上來了哈)
Stay here! I'll take your dad up, alright?
# 在農村 在家裡 經常陪一下小孩很開心的
It's really happy to be with the children more often when we're at home, in the village.
# 哦 開不開心
Oh! Are you happy?
# 開不開心
Are you?
# 她要上來
She wants to get down.
# 多開心 跑啦
She's so happy, that she runs away.
# 我要帶小孩
I go to look after her.
# 怕摔跤
Watch out! Don't fall!
# 握握手
Shake hand with me.
# 它不會 不肯
It can't, or it doesn't want to.
# 它跟公雞在一起 公雞啄它
It's with the rooster. Hey rooster! Peck it!
# 不聽話
Naughty!
# 它不理我
It ignores me.
# 送一朵花給你
We give you a flower.
# 一丟 送給它
Throw, throw it the flower.
# 問它要不要
Ask if it wants the flower.
# 跟它說 問它要不要
Say it! Ask if it wants.
# 這個 這個是公貓來的
This, this cat is male.
# 肯定不要花啦
Certainly it doesn't want a flower.
# 看到花都跑
It runs away from flowers.
# 小貓
Kitty!
# 把它撿回來
Let me pick it up.
# 啊 我把這個花花扎到你頭髮上 好不好
Ah! Let me put this flower in your hair, shall I?
# 扎到一個新花
You have a new flower.
# 不要動 不要動 不要動 別動
Don't move, don't move, don't move, don't move
# 好啦 你看一下 靚不靚
Alright! Have a look. Is it beautiful?
# 很靚哦 是不是
It's so beautiful, isn't it?
# 別坐下去 好髒 站起來
Don't sit here. It's so dirty. Stand up!
# 走啦
Let's go!
# 貓貓不要 它不要
Kitty doesn't want it, it doesn't.
# 扎到你頭髮上啦 很靚了啊
It's now in your hair. It so beautiful, isn't it?
# 要不要肉哦
Do you want some meat?
# 要不要雞腿
Or a chicken leg?
# 它不要
It doesn't.
# 一群鴨子 就剩下這兩個啦
There used to be a whole herd of ducks but these are the only two left now.
# 全部被吃光啦
All have been eaten.
# 啊~啊~啊~啊 下個蛋出來
Ah~ah~ah~ah! Lay an egg!